<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the true Episcopal religion as it was planted and set forth by our Saviour Christ ... / by W.C., student in divinity.</title>
            <author>W. C., Student in divinity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C173A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15221</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12542992</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12542992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 308:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the true Episcopal religion as it was planted and set forth by our Saviour Christ ... / by W.C., student in divinity.</title>
                  <author>W. C., Student in divinity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Chandler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62998:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE <hi>True Epiſcopal</hi> RELIGION, As it was Planted and Set forth by our Saviour Chriſt, Who Ordained the Firſt Twelve Biſhops, and afterwards maintained it by his Apoſtles againſt all his Enemies, eſpecially the Papiſts <hi>and</hi> Non-Conformiſts, Who have ſtrove to diſparage it, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> W.C. <hi>Student in Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Chandler.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62998:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62998:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION of the True Epiſcopal Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is now, was planted by <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> who buried the Body of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> The Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> being in great Perſecution, <hi>Joſeph</hi> was put into a Cell or Dungeon, and watched by the High-Prieſt; but by Providence was delivered out, and came to a place where were Ten <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> had put into a Boat without Oars, to ſhift for themſelves; into this Boat <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his Son <hi>Joſeph</hi> entred, which brought them to <hi>Marſellis</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> from whence they came into <hi>Britany,</hi> as Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> affirms out of the moſt ancient Records in the <hi>Vatican</hi> Library, of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Preaching here: his words were; <hi>Lazarus, Mary, Mary Magdalen, Martha, and Marcela, whom the Jews hated more than others, were baniſhed Jeruſalem, with Maximinus a Diſciple.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> ſets down the Year when <hi>Joſeph</hi> came into <hi>England,</hi> out of the ancient Records in the Pope's Library, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Nineteenth year of the Reign of <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperour, and in the Thirty fifth year of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I might quote many more Authors, which all agree of his coming into <hi>Britany,</hi> and planting the Chriſtian Religion; but ſure it was, he planted the Time Epiſcopal Religion here, as he had it from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which hath continued here in <hi>England</hi> ever ſince, though with much Perſecution. The Firſt Perſecution was by the coming of the <hi>Saxons.</hi> I might ſpeak at large of the <hi>Heathen</hi> Perſecutions; but I ſhall wave them, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62998:3"/>come to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Perfecutions: And firſt, by <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk, whom <hi>Gregory</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſent over to. <hi>England,</hi> to peſuade them to condeſcend to the Orders of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to unite with them; which the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Biſhops refuſed, and told them, that our Church was planted before theirs: Yet <hi>Auſtin</hi> uſes all the means he could for the bringing of them to their Society, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving procured, by means of. <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> a Meeting of divers <hi>Britiſh</hi> Biſhops, and other Principal Men of the Clergy, at a certain place in <hi>Worceſterſhire,</hi> called after upon this occaſion <hi>Auſtin's Oak;</hi> where by Perſuaſions, Threats, and. all manner of means, he endeavoured to draw the <hi>Britans</hi> to an entire Conformity with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which then was fallen from the Purlty of former Times, whereas the <hi>Britains</hi> had ſtill continued, as <hi>Geoffery of Monmouth</hi> ſaith, in the ſame Tenor of pure Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which they had received in the firſt Infancy of the Church. Their Anſwer was ſhort and peremptory, That they might not ſubmit themſelves to him, having an Archbiſhop of their own. <hi>Auſtin</hi> not diſcouraged, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured another Meeting, to which many more of the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> repaired than before; it is ſaid there were ſeven Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Before this Aſſembly certain <hi>Britains</hi> thought it good to ask Counſel of a certain Old Man, to know of him whether he thought it beſt for them to ſubmit to <hi>Auſtin,</hi> or not; he adviſed them, if he were a Man of God, to take the Courſe he ſhewed them, and to follow the ſame: and when they asked him how they ſhould diſcern whether he were ſuch an one, or no; he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this. Saying of our Saviour, <hi>Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me, for I am meek and humble of heart;</hi> if then this <hi>Auſtin</hi> be a meek and humble Man, it is an evident ſign he beareth the yoke of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but if he be ſtout and proud, he is not of God you may be ſure: This therefore is my advice; Have a care that he and his Company be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62998:3"/>firſt in the place where you meet; if then (you being the greater number) he riſe not to do you Reverence, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth you, deſpiſe you him alſo, and his Counſel. <hi>Auſtin</hi> firſt entred the Place with great pomp; and when the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Biſhops came in, never moved to riſe or ſalute them; This they taking very ill, gainſaid him in every thing, exhorting one another not to yield a jot unto him by any means; For (ſay they) he that will not dain ſo much as to riſe out of his Chair to ſalute us, how much more, when we have ſubmitted our ſelves to his Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, will he deſpiſe us, and ſet us at nought? With this Repulſe <hi>Auſtin</hi> was ſo much moved, that .he could not forbear to ſend out Threats againſt the poor <hi>Britains,</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, That they which refuſed Peace with their Friends, ſhould ſhortly find War and Enemies. How well he ſeconded his Words by Deeds, appeareth by the Words of <hi>Thomas Gray,</hi> who wrote the Chronicle about 300 years ſince. <hi>Auſtin</hi> being refuſed by the Biſhops, and other Learned, of the <hi>Britains,</hi> complained to King <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> who forthwith levied his Power, marched againſt them, and ſlew them in a moſt cruel manner, having no more regard of them than Wolves have of Sheep Their fury was ſo great againſt them, that <hi>Ethellert</hi> ſent <hi>Elfred</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland</hi> to help him, and that. <hi>Auſtin</hi> met them at <hi>Cheſter</hi> upon this occaſion. The <hi>Britains</hi> received a great Overthrow; for beſides an infinite number of Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, were ſlain a great Company of Monks, no leſs than 1100, who never ſought at all, but by Prayer. Of all other of the Clergy, the greateſt ſpleen was againſt them, as the greateſt Wrong-doers, becauſe they would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive quietly the yoke of a Forreign uſurping Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, intruded upon them.</p>
            <p>The next Perſecution was by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> about the year 1554 who hurned the Twelve Biſhops and Doctors which compiled the Book of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> with many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62998:4"/>more of the Clergy, and of the Commonalty; till a Gentleman told the Queen, If ſhe uſed this way of Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhe would weaken the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> for all that beheld them admired them, that Death being ſo ſanctified to them, that they ſeemed not to feel the Flames. This Perſecution was terrible for the time it laſted; but it pleaſed God to take her away in a very ſhort time, and bring in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of happy Memory, who eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the Lpiſcopal Religion again, with the Book of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> which Queen <hi>Mary</hi> had burned; whom God bleſſed with a Reign of 44 years.</p>
            <p>The next Perſecution, deſigned by the Papiſts, was in King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, in 1603. when they had plotted by Gunpowder (which was laid for that purpoſe under the Parliament-houſe) to blow up the King, and the Chief of the Nobility of this Land. This deviliſh Plot, had it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken effect, had been the worſt of all the Perfections; for it would have taken away their Lives in a moment, ſo that they ſhould have no Meditation for their Souls good. This Plot aimed to deſtroy the Soul, as well as the Body ; but, Melted be God, it was diſcovered.</p>
            <p>The next Plot that was by the Antichriſtian Papiſts was in <hi>Ireland.</hi> This was an inhumane Perſecution, ſuch as the very Heathen would abhor. They rebelled againſ their King, ripped up their Women with Child, and ſlew their Husdands at their own door.</p>
            <p>The next Perſecution was againſt the King and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by the Nonconformists, eſpecially the Presbyterians; for they firſt broke the Unity of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and cauſed a Rebellion in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by raiſing an Army againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, one of the beſt Kings that ever Reigned in the World, about the year 1640. and after purſued the Rebellion, and raiſed an Army in <hi>England,</hi> and fought againſt the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and killed many of his Loyal Subjects, and purſued
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62998:4"/>their King until they had brought him to the Block. This Perſecution was againſt; the Church, as well as the King; they murdered the Archiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and Dr. <hi>Huet,</hi> and depoſed the Biſhops of all their Spiritual Employments; and then they fell to Sacriledge, to rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of the Church, aboliſhed the Common Service Book, and ſold the Biſhops Lands, and moſt of the Church-lands, and put down the Diſcipline of the Church as much as they could, imitating the Papiſts in many things, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Rebellion, Murder, Treaſon, Sacrilege, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; pretending, as the Papiſts do now, all was for the Glory of God, and for the Reformation of the Church.</p>
            <p>Epiſcopal Religion was ordained by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who ordained the firſt twelve Biſhops; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Apoſtles gave order for the placing of Biſhops in many Churches, for the well ordering of the Church. <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> Diſciple of Chriſt, one that buried him; planted our Church of <hi>England</hi> according to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way, which hath continued for above 1600 years a true Church for the moſt part, as many Hiſtorians write, notwithſtanding much Perſecution by the Heathen and the Antichriſtians; and yet they have enjoyed and kept up this Church in ſome corners of this Land, till a Change of Government hath hapned, and the Governours have been converted by it and have defended it from evil Men. Now I beſeech you all, the good People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> from the King to the beggar, to take eſpecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Perſecution of this innocent Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which is the trueſt mark of a true Church.</p>
            <p>You ſee how <hi>Satan</hi> by the Heathen, and by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and by the Nonconformiſt, hath perſecuted it to the utmoſt of his power; yet God of his Mercy and Providence hath defended it againſt all the fury of the Enemies: Therefore all good People of England, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort your ſelves, and. ſerve God in this Church with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62998:5"/>rejoycing and praiſing God, for preſerving and defending this Church againſt all his Enemies. Wherefore you may be aſſured, as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> told the <hi>Jews, this work is of God, and it cannot be overthrown; for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if it be of themſelves it will conic to nought; but if it be of God, you cannot overthrthrow it, leſt you be found Fighters againſt God. Charles</hi> the Firſt ſealed it with his Royal Blood; the twelve Biſhops and Doctors ſealed this Church by Fire and Blood in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Reign: <hi>The Blood of the Martyrs is the ſeed and ſeal of a true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now ſpeak ſomething of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> which was planted by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as moſt Hiſtorians write, becauſe he commends it in I <hi>Rom.</hi> in theſe words, <hi>I thank God thy Faith is ſpoken of throughout the whole World;</hi> and ſo it continued a true Church for near 600 years, having above Gixty Biſhops, whereof <hi>Linus</hi> was the firſt, whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of in his Epiſtles. All thoſe Biſhops were godly Men, being ſubject to the Civil Magiſtrate. <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> the Second, in his days, perceiving that <hi>Maurice</hi> the Emperour went about, to make and eſtabliſh an Univerſal Biſhop, very much oppoſed it, and decreed, That no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, no not the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelf, ought to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop;</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Gregory</hi> his Succeſſor writeth, That none of his Predeceſſors ever conſented to uſe ſo proſane a Title. And alſo the ſaid <hi>Gregory</hi> writeth to the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who was willing to take that Title upon him, <hi>What wilt thou anſwer to Chriſt the Head of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, that thus goeſt about by the Name of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop to make all his Members ſubject to thee? Whom doſt thou imitate in ſo perverſe a Name, but</hi> Lucifer, <hi>that would have been ſingular, alone, above all his fellow Angels? Sabinianus</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Gregory,</hi> and after him <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, who obtained of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperor, as afterwards is ſet down, That the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be called <hi>the Head of the Church:</hi> Since which time the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62998:5"/>Pope hath been called <hi>the Prince of Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Supreme Head of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church;</hi> Titles due only to Chriſt himſelf, the Great Biſhop of our Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cedrenus</hi> ſetteth forth <hi>Phocas</hi> to be a Wine-bibber, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Women, a bloody Man, fierce, without Mercy, cruel of Manners, an Heretick: and <hi>Theophylact Simocatta</hi> deſcribeth him after this manner; A <hi>Caledonian</hi> Tyrant, covered with Iron, in a manner barbarous, of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Cyclops,</hi> a <hi>Centaur</hi> in Purple, moſt petulant, whoſe chief ſtrife was for the Kingdom of Drunkenneſs: A fit Man to be Antichriſt's Midwife, to bring him into the World! The Authority of the former Biſhops ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no farther than unto Matters of Religion; they were ſubject to the Emperours, ſome of them created by him, as <hi>Paget</hi> affirms in his <hi>Hiſtory of the ſundry ſorts of Churches,</hi> and denied the Popes Supremacy, with their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Worſhip, introduced by <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, by calling Councils of a few <hi>Italian</hi> Biſhops, and turning out many good Biſhops, which would not conſent to their creating of Sin: And ſome they murdered, as <hi>Paget</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, becauſe they withſtood their wicked Decrees, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> who enacted a Canon, <hi>That the Traditions of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>muſt be honoured and embraced with the like honour and reverence as the Holy Scriptures are honoured.</hi> In this Council, their firſt Sin they created and decreed, was for <hi>Image-Worſhip,</hi> contrary to the Second Commandment, 2. <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> contrary to the Practice of the Church, the Examples of Holy Men, and to the Doctrine of the Holy Scriptures. 3. The <hi>Propitiatory Sacrifice in the Maſs,</hi> which derogateth from Chriſts Sacrifice once offered for us 4. <hi>Communion in One Kind,</hi> directly againſt Chriſts Precept in the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Let no man beguile you of your reward in a voluntary humility and worſhipping of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, intruding into thoſe things which they have not ſeen,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62998:6"/>vainly puffed up by their fleſhly mind.</hi> In this Council they alſo decreed, That all Biſhops and Miniſters muſt teach the People to worſhip Saints, Images, and Angels, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, and of St. <hi>John</hi> the Divine, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. who ſaith, <hi>I fell at the Angels feet, to worſhip him; and he ſaid unto me, See thou do it not; I am thy fellow-ſervant, and of thy brethren, that have the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus: Worſhip God.</hi> Here, good People, take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, their Decrees are quite againſt the Word of God: They command Angel worſhip, and the Angel tells <hi>John, See thou do it not, I am thy fellow-ſervant; worſhip God.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.3. <hi>Let no man deceive you by any means; for that day ſhall not come, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept there come a falling awry firſt, and that man of ſin be revealed, the ſon of perdition, who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped; ſo that he, as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that he is God;</hi> and ſo on: and then at <hi>ver.</hi> 12. he concludes with theſe words; <hi>For this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhould believe a lie, that they all might be damned who believe not the truth, but had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Myſtery of Iniquity began to work in the time of <hi>Gregory the Great,</hi> the ſecond Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> before <hi>Boniface</hi> the firſt Antichriſtian Biſhop. The ſaid <hi>Gregory,</hi> writing to the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ſharply repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends him in the words before quoted; and he ſaith alſo, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call himſelf</hi> Univerſal Biſhop, <hi>or deſire ſo to be called in the pride of his heart, is the fore-runner of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</hi> I may by no means omit again to remember you, what St. <hi>Paul</hi> writes to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> in the place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cited, from <hi>ver.</hi> 1. to 12. of that Chapter: upon which St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Civitate Dei,</hi> hath theſe words; <hi>This Scripture</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doubtleſs is meant of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt:</hi> And again, <hi>Truly</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I am utterly ignorant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62998:6"/>what others Conjectures are hereof; but I will not be ſilent: Some ſay St.</hi> Paul <hi>ſpake of the ſtate of</hi> Rome, <hi>and would not be plainer, leſt he ſhould incur a ſlander, that he wiſhed</hi> Romes <hi>Empine an evil Fortune.</hi> The ſame Father hath given his opinion, That theſe Words, <hi>He that withhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhall let, till he be taken out of the way, and then the wicked man ſhall be revealed,</hi> are meant of Antichriſt: <hi>No man doubteth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that this may not unfitly be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of</hi> Rome: As if he had ſaid, He that now reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhall reign, until he be taken away. This may be meant of thoſe good Emperors that ſhould be taken away by death; and then that wicked Man was revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> who was the Father of Antichriſt, and created <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> an Univerſal Biſhop of the Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped; ſo that he, as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</hi> I ſhall give you a Definition of the God here ſpoken of, Temporal and Spiritual; and firſt of the Temporal God. <hi>Moſes,</hi> in one of his Books, ſpeaking of the Temporal Gods, ſays, <hi>I have ſaid, you are Gods, but you ſhall die like Men, ye Princes ſhall fall like others.</hi> Here God is pleaſed to call Emperors, Kings, and Princes, <hi>Gods,</hi> becauſe they execute Gods Will upon Earth. Here the Man of Sin exalteth himſelf above the Temporal Gods, in placing and diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them at his pleaſure; he maketh them believe that he can put them into the ſtate of Damnation, or abſolve them, at his pleaſure; whereas for the firſt 600 years, more than ſixty Biſhops were ſubject to their Emperours and Kings, and many of them Ordained and Inſtituted by their Order, till <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, and <hi>Phocas</hi> that wicked Emperour.</p>
            <p>Again, He exalteth himſelf above the great God of Heaven and Earth. Chriſt refuſed to be called <hi>Good,</hi> and told them, <hi>There was none good but God;</hi> but the Man of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62998:7"/>Sin, the Pope, thinks it not a ſufficient Honour to be called <hi>Good,</hi> or <hi>Holy;</hi> but <hi>Moſt Holy:</hi> a Title due to none but the Great God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Here in this very Particular he exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped.</p>
            <p>Again, He is ſo uncharitable, as ſhews he is nothing of a true Chriſtian; for he will Excommunicate the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches from the higheſt to the loweſt, tho he never knew any of them, nor their Doctrine or Manners, and does his endeavour to ſend them to Hell, tho we know his Power is nothing againſt our Church. Whereas the Great God ſaith, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord, I deſire not the death of a ſinner, but that all ſhould come to repent and be ſaved.</hi> And the ſaid Pope, the Man of Sin, hath Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated all God's Vicegerents of this Land, from Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to our gracious King that now is. Here the Luciſerian Biſhop ſhews how he exalts himſelf above all that is called God, in Excommunicating Gods Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, when no doubt but many of them may belong to the Election written in the Lambs Book of Life before the Foundation of the World. Here the Man of Sin touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Wiſdom of the Godhead, in putting into the ſtate of Damnation thoſe whom God hath elected; for, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of God's Elect? It is God that juſtifieth.</hi> In this <hi>he exalteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above all that is called God; ſo that he, as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</hi> But you will ſay, That the Temple of God was at Jeruſalem. St. <hi>Auſtuſtine,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Civitate Dei,</hi> gives you his Judgment in that; <hi>In Templum Deum,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>In ſome Temple of God:</hi> And he adds, <hi>It could not be meant of the Temple at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>becauſe</hi> Titus Veſpaſian <hi>had deſtroyed and ſacked it, ſo that there was not left one ſtone upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which was not thrown down: nor of an Heatheniſh Idols Temple; for that was no Temple of God: but he muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62998:7"/>ſit in ſome Chriſtian Temple, which may not unfitly be applied to</hi> Rome. So he. Now St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and many of the Learned, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> meant this of that great Cathedral, St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Rome,</hi> which may not unfitly be called <hi>the Temple of God,</hi> becauſe for the firſt 600 years after Chriſt, Religion did ſlow plentifully from thence into many Parts of the World, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. that <hi>their faith was ſpoken of thorow the whole world:</hi> And there was <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour converted to the Faith, in whoſe Reign <hi>Arius</hi> broached his Hereſie in <hi>Africa;</hi> whereof when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> heard, he ſaid, <hi>There was no true ſerving of God without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Love:</hi> and thereupon he made a Decree, and Sealed it with his own Seal, in theſe VVords; <hi>I ſtraightly charge and command more than</hi> 300 <hi>Biſhops, that you go into</hi> Africa, <hi>and ſummon</hi> Arius, <hi>and examine his Doctrine, whether it be according to the Word of God, or no; and if not, to brand him for an Heretick, that it proceed no further:</hi> as <hi>Euſebins</hi> ſaith, in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhere was St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> when <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> executed his Eccleſiaſtical Power? which Authority has been claimed and exerciſed by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> but ſince <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, who was made by that wicked Emperour Univerſal Biſhop. And without doubt, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rome</hi> is that Temple of God where Antichriſt and the Man of Sin ſhould ſit, according to St. <hi>Paul: ſo that he, as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</hi> But you may ſay, How doth he ſhew himſelf that he is God?</p>
            <p>I aſwer thus; Here he ſits in his great magnificent Throne, in his rich Robes, his Triple Crown on his Head, and in his pretended <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, where he ſhews himſelf that he is God, in bleſſing whom he pleaſes (but not without Money) and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing whom he pleaſeth. Here he makes his unlawful Decrees to be believed and honoured equal with the Scripture, upon pain of his Curſe if they do not. Here they muſt kiſs his Feet, give him his Godhead Title <hi>Moſt Holy,</hi> which is due to none but God. Here he delivers Souls out of Purgatory, makes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences and Pardons for Sins paſt and to come: Here they buy their Sins, and the Man of Sin ſells their Sins; but non of theſe without great Sums of Money. In all theſe things he ſhews that he is God, becauſe he can put whom he pleaſeth into the State of Salvation, and whom he will into the State of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62998:8"/>nation, and for Money forgive them their Sins paſt and to come. I have hear ſhewn you, <hi>that that wicked man is reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the man of Sin, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the Spirit of his mouth, and with the brightneſs of his coming; whoſe coming is after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonders. For this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould believe a lye, that they all might be damned who believe not the truth, but have pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> Beloved Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I beſeech you in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you do not adhere to the Man of Sin, nor believe his deceivable ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Doctrine, that you have no part with thoſe of whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>who believe lies, and believe not the truth, but have pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the Man of Sin ſtiles himſelf the Vicar of Chriſt, and Head of the Church; but follows not Chriſt, neither by Example not Doctrine: Chriſt was humble, meek, and lowly, and taught us to pray for them that hate us: The Man of Sin, contrary to Chriſt's Doctrine, curſes them that hate him, and many of them that love him, if they diſpleaſe him. The Apoſtles told our Saviour he ſhould command ſtrange Fires to conſume his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; he told them, <hi>they knew not what Spirit they were of, he came not to deſtroy Men, but to ſave them:</hi> The Man of Sin, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this Doctrine, by his Perſecution burns many of Chriſt's Servants by Fires, as in the time of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> The Apoſtles asked Chriſt who ſhould be greateſt; Chriſt told them, <hi>That he that would be greateſt ſhould be as him that ſerves,</hi> or Servant to all: The Man of Sin maketh himſelf greateſt, and above his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Biſhops, yea above all that is called God, contrary to Chriſts Doctrine.</p>
            <p>You ſee how he proves himſelf to be the Man of Sin St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> by his Wicked Practiſe, as in tolerating Perjury, Rebellion, Treaſon, and Murder, in this late Plot againſt our Sovereign Lord the King, and his Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to deſtroy the Government head of Church and State.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord bleſs our Sovereign Lord the King, the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and all the Loyal Subjects of <hi>England.</hi> The Lord keep us all from any adherence with the Man of Sin, and that we believe not his deceivable lying Doctrine, leſt we ſhould come into the ſtate of the Damned, which St. <hi>Paul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſpeaketh on. And Lord, we thank thy gracious Majeſty, that thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62998:8"/>us out of the hands of the Man of Sin, and of his Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Deſigns, and from all the Plots our Enemies have had ever ſince we have been a Church. O Lord, I beſeech thee to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue thy good hand of Providence over us thy unworthy Servants, in preſerving us from all dangers that may fall upon us, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our Sins. O Lord, give every one of us ſuch a meaſure of Grace as thou ſhalt think fit, that we may hate Sin, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry falſe way, which hinders thy Bleſſings from us.</p>
            <p>The Lord grant, that our Sovereign Lord the King, and his Succeſſor, may take ſuch care over this preſent Church, that as God ſhall deliver the Enemies of this Church into his hand, they may have Juſtice done according to the Will, of God, that ſo he may truly be called <hi>The Defender of the Faith</hi> in Heaven, as well as on Earth. And all this we beg for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>'s ſake, our Bleſſed Redeemer.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Presbyterian Government defective, in breaking the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, they brake their Oath of Allegiance with their King; then the Miniſters broke their Oath of Canonical Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with their Biſhop, which are both Perjury: Then they raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Army againſt their King, both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and in <hi>England,</hi> which is Rebellion, which is <hi>as the ſin of Witchcraft;</hi> then they Fought againſt the Kings Perſon, which is Treaſon, a crying ſin; then they turned out their Biſhops out of their Spiritual Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and ſold the Church Lands, and took away the Diſcipline of the Church and Common Prayer, which was compoſed by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and robbed Gods Church, which is Sacrilege; then they purſued the King with their Armies, and took him, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him, which is Treaſon in the higheſt degree: And all this, as they pretended, was for a Reformation, which in the end proved a Deformation of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Judge in your ſelves what Reformation could be, when all their Actions determined in ſins, and of a deep Dye; as Perjury and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, Sacriledge, Treaſon, and Murder: All which proceed from the Spiritual Man of ſin, the Devil, who is the cauſe of all Sin and Diviſion. Hear what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; <hi>Mark thoſe that cauſe Diviſion and avoid them; for they ſerve not the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Who then muſt they ſerve, but the Devil? From the Presbyterians,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62998:9"/>after they had broke the Unity of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I ſay, from that evil Root, ſprung the Independant, Anabaptiſt, and the Quaker; and all theſe are divided within themſelves in Judgment of their Religion: There is the Presbyterian againſt the Independant and Anababtiſt, and the Anabaptiſt againſt the Independant and the Presbyterian, and the Quaker againſt them all, and all theſe againſt; the true Epiſcopal Church; as I told them upon a Diſpute, there was <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſe</hi> and <hi>Manaſſe</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Juda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they were Gods Diſciples, they would love one another; but I fear they are not, becauſe they have not Charity one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another. St. <hi>John</hi> in Epiſtle 1. Chap. 2. ver. 10. ſaith, <hi>They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us;</hi> for if they had bin of us, they would no doubt have kept with us.</p>
               <p>Now for all thoſe crying Sins I have repeated, I wiſh from my heart they are not guilty of them; and what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is not out of any malice; but as they were Brethren once, to inform them of their Error and Sin, wiſhing their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance might be their Puniſhment; for I believe that many of them are civil honeſt-meaning Men; but they erre not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true meaning of the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Now I beſeech the Lord God of Peace and Love, That he would give thoſe Diſſenters ſuch a meaſure of Grace, that they may ſee their Errors, and repent, and come into the true Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Church they went out of: which hath been proved a true Church by Fire and Sword, as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> told the <hi>Jews, That if the work were of God, they could not overthrow it, leſt they were found fighters againſt God:</hi> Therefore have a care that you ſpeak no evil nor Fight no more againſt this Church, leſt you be found Fighters againſt God. Now the Lord grant that theſe Diſſenters may come into the true Church they went out of, and conform to the Government of the Church, which is allowed by God and the King; and there they may exerciſe their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Parts God hath given them, that they together with us may ſerve God with one Heart and with one Mind, <hi>holding the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace and Love, without which no Man ſhall ſee the Lord:</hi> Which the Lord grant of his mercy through the Merits of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
